Inventory of the Merrill J. Mattes Papers, 1935-1964
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Merrill J. Mattes papers
1935-1964
Mattes, Merrill J.
00120
7.45 cubic feet (16 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Biography of Merrill J. Mattes
Merrill John Mattes (1910- ), a historian, worked for the National Park Service (NPS) for 30 years, beginning as a ranger at Yellowstone National Park in 1935. He was superintendent of Scotts Bluff National Monument from 1935-1946, acting custodian of Fort Laramie National Monument (later Fort Laramie National Historic Site) beginning in 1938, and was acting historian for Fort Laramie from 1939-1946. Mattes was regional historian at the NPS Region 2 office in Omaha, Nebraska from 1946-1966, chief of history and historic architecture in San Francisco, California from 1966-1971, and manager of the historic preservation team at the NPS Denver Service Center from 1971-1975. He became an independent historical consultant in 1976. In 1944, Mattes testified as an expert witness against the state of Wyoming's lawsuit challenging the creation of the Jackson Hole National Monument.
Scope and Content
Collection is chiefly materials on Wyoming including copies of Mattes' National Park Service files of correspondence, memorandums, maps, reports, photographs, negatives, legal documents, and printed materials related to Fort Laramie, Yellowstone National Park, Grand Teton National Park, Jackson Hole National Monument, Fort Phil Kearny, Fort Caspar, Fort Bridger and the Oregon Trail. Collection also includes two boxes of note cards containing bibliographic citations and research notes on the history of Jackson Hole and the fur trade.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Merrill J. Mattes at the date of processing.
Additional Information
Finding aid available in repository.
Acquisition Information
The collection was received from Merrill J. Mattes in 1949 and 1977.
Access Terms
United States. National Park Service. Region Two.; Historic sites -- Wyoming -- Conservation and restoration.; Historic buildings -- Wyoming -- Conservation and restoration.; Fur trade -- Wyoming -- Jackson Hole.; Trails -- Wyoming.; Trails -- West (U.S.); National parks and reserves -- Wyoming.; National monuments -- Wyoming.; Fort Laramie (Wyo.: Fort); Fort Laramie National Historic Site (Wyo.); Fort Bridger (Wyo.); Fort Caspar (Wyo.); Fort Phil Kearny (Wyo.); Yellowstone National Park.; Grand Teton National Park (Wyo.); Jackson Hole (Wyo.); Jackson Hole National Monument.; Oregon National Historic Trail.; Photographs.; Negatives.; Memorandums.; Notes.; Bibliographies.; Legal documents.; Historians.
Environment and Conservation; National Parks; Land Use; Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences; Education; Wyoming
Container List
- "Sutler's Store at Fort Laramie" (Folder F775-L)
- "Jackson Hole, Crossroads of the West Fur Trade, 1807-1840 (Folder W994-jh)
- "Fort Laramie and the Forty-Niners" (Folder F775-L)
- File Folders:
  - Grand Teton - Articles about Park. 6 pieces (Box 1)
  - Grand Teton - Congressional Reports. 2 pieces (Box 1)
  - Grand Teton - History - General. 23 pieces (Box 1)
  - Grand Teton - History - Fur Trade. 29 pieces (Box 1)
  - Grand Teton - Jackson Hole National Monument Articles. 8 pieces (Box 1)
  - Grand Teton - Menor's Ferry. 7 pieces (Box 1)
  - Grand Teton - "Nature Notes." 2 pieces (Box 1)
  - Grand Teton - Pamphlets. 18 pieces (Box 1)
  - Grand Teton - "Photographs." 80 pieces (Box 2)
  - Grand Teton - Jackson Hole - Correspondence. 26 pieces (Box 2)
  - Wyoming - Fort Bridger. 5 pieces (Box 2)
  - Wyoming - Fort Casper. 1 piece (Box 2)
  - Wyoming - Fort Phil Kearney. 9 pieces (Box 2)
  - Wyoming - General. 47 pieces (Box 2)
  - Wyoming - General Literature, Misc. data, correspondence 16 pieces. (Box 2)
  - Wyoming - Jackson County. 2 pieces (Box 3)
  - Wyoming - Photographs - Grand Tetons. 4 pieces (Box 3)
  - Yellowstone - Articles. 6 pieces (Box 3)
  - Yellowstone - Diamond Jubilee Material. 4 pieces (Box 3)
  - Yellowstone - History. 21 pieces (Box 3)
  - Yellowstone - Maps. 11 pieces (Box 3)
  - Yellowstone - "Nature Notes." 7 pieces (Box 3)
  - Yellowstone - Pamphlets. 6 pieces (Box 3)
- Photographs:
  - Idaho - Blackfoot. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 2. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 3)
  - Idaho - Drummond. No. of Packets: 6. No. of Photos: 17. No. of Negs.: 6 (Box 3)
  - Idaho - Fort Hall. No. of Packets: 4. No. of Photos: 6. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 3)
  - Idaho - Fort Henry. No. of Packets: 5. No. of Photos: 5. No. of Negs.: 5 (Box 3)
  - Idaho - Spalding. No. of Packets: 3. No. of Photos: 3. No. of Negs.: 3 (Box 3)
  - Kansas - El Quartelejo. No. of Packets: 1. No. of Photos: 1 No. of Negs.: 1 (Box 3)
  - Montana - Bighorn Canyon. No. of Packets: 1. No. of Photos: 1. No. of Negs.: 0 (Box 3)
  - Montana - Buffalo Jump-off, Browning. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 7. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 3)
  - Nebraska - Chadron. No. of Packets: 6. No. of Photos: 6. No. of Negs.: 6 (Box 3)
  - North Dakota - Fort Union. No. of Packets: 4. No. of Photos: 6. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 3)
  - Oregon - Fort Dalles. No. of Packets: 2. No of Photos: 3. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 4)
  - Oregon - Oregon City. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 3. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 4)
  - Oregon - Oregon Trail, Columbia River. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 4 No. of Negs.: 2. (Box 4)
  - Oregon - Seaside. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 2. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 4)
  - South Dakota - Spearfish. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 2. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 4)
  - Washington - Fort Columbia. No. of Packets: 1. No. of Photos: 1. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 4)
  - Washington - Fort Vancouver. No. of Packets: 1. No. of Photos: 1. No. of Negs.: 1 (Box 4)
  - Washington - Fort Walla Walla. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 3. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 4)
  - Wyoming - Activities. No. of Packets: 3. No. of Photos: 5. No. of Negs.: 3 (Box 4)
  - Wyoming - Alcova Resevoir. No. of Packets: 16. No. of Photos: 10. No. of Negs.: 16 (Box 4)
  - Wyoming - Anchor Resevoir. No. of Packets: 37. No. of Photos: 0. No. of Negs.: 37 (Box 4)
  - Wyoming - Arvada. No. of Packets: 1. No. of Photos: 1. No. of Negs.: 1 (Box 4)
  - Wyoming - Bennett Buttes. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 3. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 4)
  - Wyoming - Big Horn River Basin. No. of Packets: 12. No. of Photos: 24. No. of Negs.: 11 (Box 4)
  - Wyoming - Big Sandy Resevoir. No. of Packets: 5. No. of Photos: 14. No. of Negs.: 5 (Box 4)
  - Wyoming - Boysen Resevoir. No. of Packets: 23. No. of Photos: 11. No. of Negs.: 23 (Box 4)
  - Wyoming - Buffalo. No. of Packets: 3. No. of Photos: 6. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - "Buffalo Bill." No. of Packets: 4. No. of Photos: 7. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Casper. No. of Packets: 5. No. of Photos: 6. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Castle Gardens. No. of Packets: 7. No. of Photos: 9. No. of Negs.: 9 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Camp Connor (Fort Connor). No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 2. No. of Negs.: 3 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Camp Stambaugh. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 2. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Charts, Maps, Plans. No. of Packets: 1. No. of Photos: 1. No. of Negs.: 1 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Cheyene. No. of Packets: 7. No. of Photos: 9. No. of Negs.: 10 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Chugwater. No. of Packets: 5. No. of Photos: 10. No. of Negs.: 8 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Church Butte. No. of Packets: 6. No. of Photos: 6. No. of Neg.: 6 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Cody-Shoshone River. No. of Packets: 5. No. of Photos: 0. No. of Negs.: 5 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Colter's Hell. No. of Packets: 23. No. of Photos: 25. No. of Negs.: 23 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Connor Battlefield. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 5. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Crowheart Butte. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 5. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Daniel. No. of Packets: 4. No. of Photos: 6. No. of Negs.: 6 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - DeGerling Quarry. No. of Packets: 4. No. of Photos: 8. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Devil's Gate. No. of Packets: 6. No. of Photos: 8. No. of Negs.: 5 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Dinwoody. No. of Packets: 11. No. of Photos: 116. No. of Negs.: 11 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming - Dullknife Battlefield. No. of Packets: 11. No. of Photos: 37. No. of Negs.: 11 (Box 6)
  - Wyoming - Fort Fetterman. No. of Packets: 17. No. of Photos: 24. No. of Negs.: 18 (Box 6)
  - Wyoming - Fort Bridger. No. of Packets: 23. No. of Photos: 39. No. of Negs.: 30 (Box 6)
  - Wyoming - Fort Brown. No. of Packets: 1. No. of Photos: 1. No. of Negs.: 1 (Box 6)
  - Wyoming - Fort Fred Steele. No. of Packets: 7. No. of Photos: 7. No. of Negs.: 8 (Box 6)
  - Wyoming - Fort Halleck. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 2. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 6)
  - Wyoming - Fort Laramie. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 3. No. of Negs.: 3 (Box 6)
  - Wyoming - Fort McKenzie. No. of Packets: 3. No. of Photos: 4. No. of Negs.: 3 (Box 6)
  - Wyoming - Fort Phil Kearney. No. of Packets: 49. No. of Photos: 51. No. of Negs.: 11 (Box 6)
  - Wyoming - Fort Platte. No. of Packets: 1. No. of Photos: 1. No. of Negs.: 1 (Box 6)
  - Wyoming - Fort Reno. No. of Packets: 4. No. of Photos: 4. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 6)
  - Wyoming - Fort Washakie. No. of Packets: 21. No. of Photos: 39. No. of Negs.: 26 (Box 7)
  - Wyoming - Glendo. No. of Packets: 8. No. of Photos: 8. No. of Negs.: 8 (Box 7)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. General. No. of Packets: 44. No. of Photos: 66. No. of Negs.: 49 (Box 7)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Battle of Pierre's Hole. No. of Packets: 9. No. of Photos: 9. No. of Negs.: 9 (Box 7)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Colter Bay. No. of Packets: 9. No. of Photos: 15. No. of Negs.: 9 (Box 7)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Colter Pageant. No. of Packets: 3. No. of Photos: 3. No. of Negs.: 3 (Box 7)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Colter Rock (Stone). No. of Packets: 13. No. of Photos: 14. No. of Negs.: 13 (Box 7)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Cunningham Ranch. No. of Packets: 13. No. of Photos: 14. No. of Negs.: 13 (Box 7)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Feuz Ranch. No. of Packets: 18. No. of Photos: 18. No. of Negs.:18 (Box 7)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Fort Bonneville. No. of Packets: 8. No. of Photos: 9. No. of Negs.: 8 (Box 7)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Cros Ventre Area. No. of Packets: 11. No. of Photos: 11. No. of Negs.: 11 (Box 7)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Hoback River. No. of Packets: 12. No. of Photos: 14. No. of Negs.: 13 (Box 7)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Jackson Hole Highway. No. of Packets: 4. No. of Photos: 4. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 8)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Menor's Ferry. No. of Packets: 25. No. of Photos: 28. No. of Negs.: 23 (Box 8)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Mormon Row. No. of Packets: 4. No. of Photos: 4. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 8)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Museum Exhibits. No. of Packets: 16. No. of Photos: 21. No. of Negs.: 17 (Box 8)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Owen Wister's Cabin, R Lazy S Ranch. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 4. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 8)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Shoshone Canyon. No. of Packets: 3. No. of Photos: 3. No. of Negs.: 3 (Box 8)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Teton Range. No. of Packets: 33. No. of Photos: 34. No. of Negs.: 33 (Box 8)
  - Wyoming - Grand Teton National Park. Wyoming Historical Society at Cody, Annual Meeting. No. of Packets: 5. No. of Photos: 5. No. of Negs.: 5 (Box 8)
  - Wyoming - Green River Rendezvous Site. No. of Packets: 25. No. of Photos: 25. No. of Negs.: 25 (Box 8)
  - Wyoming - Guernsey Reservoir. No. of Packets: 5. No. of Photos: 5. No. of Negs.: 5 (Box 8)
  - Wyoming - Hells Half Acre. No. of Packets: 4. No. of Photos: 11. No. of Negs.: 5 (Box 8)
  - Wyoming - Indian Medicine Wheel. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 2. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 9)
  - Wyoming - Jackson Collection. No. of Packets: 1. No. of Photos: 1. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 9)
  - Wyoming - Lake DeSmet. No. of Packets: 8. No. of Photos: 23. No. of Negs.: 8 (Box 9)
  - Wyoming - Lander. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 2. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 9)
  - Wyoming - Laramie. No. of Packets: 11. No. of Photos: 14. No. of Negs.: 13 (Box 9)
  - Wyoming - Mayoworth Village. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 6. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 9)
  - Wyoming - North Platte River Basin. No. of Packets: 46. No. of Photos: 61. No. of Negs.: 54 (Box 9)
  - Wyoming - Oregon Trail. General. No. of Packets: 21. No. of Photos: 47. No. of Negs.: 38 (Box 9)
  - Wyoming - Oregon Trail. Independence Rock. No. of Packets: 4. No. of Photos: 6. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 9)
  - Wyoming - Oregon Trail. Register Cliff. No. of Packets: 24. No. of Photos: 31. No. of Negs.: 24 (Box 9)
  - Wyoming - Oregon Trail. South Pass. No. of Packets: 10. No. of Photos: 22. No. of Negs.: 18 (Box 9)
  - Wyoming - Portraits. No. of Packets: 16. No. of Photos: 18. No. of Negs.: 16 (Box 9)
  - Wyoming - Powder River Division (with Captions Sheet). No. of Packets: 96. No. of Photos: 1. No. of Negs.: 104 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - South Pass City. No. of Packets: 13. No. of Photos: 29. No. of Negs.: 13 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - Spanish Diggings. No. of Packets: 11. No. of Photos: 11. No. of Negs.: 11 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - State Park at Ranchester. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 3. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - Thermopolis. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 0. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - Tongue River, South Fork. No. of Packets: 19. No. of Photos: 16. No. of Negs.: 22 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - Torrington. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 4. No. of Negs.: 2 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - Upper Platte Sub-Basin. No. of Packets: 7. No. of Photos: 7. No. of Negs.: 7 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - Wagon Box Fight Site. No. of Packets: 5. No. of Photos: 9. No. of Negs.: 11 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - Wapiti Ranger Station. No. of Packets: 2. No. of Photos: 4. No. of Negs.: 4 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - Wind River Basin (with captions Sheet). No. of Packets: 98. No. of Photos: 98. No. of Negs.: 107 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - Yellowstone National Park. No. of Packets: 35. No. of Photos: 49. No. of Negs.: 38 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - Yellowstone National Park. Clarks Fork. No. of Packets: 55. No. of Photos: 55. No. of Negs.: 55 (Box 10)
  - Wyoming - Miscellaneous Wyoming. No. of Packets: 24. No. of Photos: 28. No. of Negs.: 26 (Box 10)
- Research Note Cards:
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. A. 10 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. B. 25 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. C. 19 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. D. 16 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. E. 10 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. F. 7 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. G. 15 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. H. 24 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. I. 6 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. J. 4 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. K. 3 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. L. 8 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. M. 15 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. Mc. 1 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. N. 5 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. O. 5 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. P. 8 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. Q. - cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. R. 12 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. S. 14 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. T. 7 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. U. - cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. V. 5 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. W. 23 cards (Box 11)
  - Bibliography - Jackson Hole. XYZ. 13 cards (Box 11)
  - Maps. 27 cards (Box 12)
  - Fur Trade. 33 cards (Box 12)
  - Jackson Hole. 18 cards (Box 12)
  - Biography. 31 cards (Box 12)
  - 1807 Colter. 34 cards (Box 12)
  - 1811 Hoback. 8 cards (Box 12)
  - 1811 Hunt. 18 cards (Box 12)
  - 1812 Stuart. 4 cards (Box 12)
  - 1818 McKenzie. 10 cards (Box 12)
  - 1824 Smith. 27 cards (Box 12)
  - 1825 Bridger. 6 cards (Box 12)
  - 1827. 15 cards (Box 12)
  - 1829 Jackson. 14 cards (Box 12)
  - 1830 Jackson. 11 cards (Box 12)
  - 1831 Fitzpatrick. 10 cards (Box 12)
  - 1832 Sublette. 31 cards (Box 12)